<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Starting Point - India</title><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/feeds/india.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.nacnez.com/</id><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>My India changing</title><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/india-extreme.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Srinivas Narayanan</name></author><id>tag:www.nacnez.com,2022-04-25:/india-extreme.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Changing face of India - getting extreme&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a write up on how I feel about my India changing in the context of religion. This is just a representation of how I feel. If it makes sense to you then you can consider listening to it, else you can surely ignore it (not that I need to say this &lt;span class="emoji"&gt;😅&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-life-religion"&gt;My life &amp;amp; religion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally don't parade the fact that I am a Hindu. I am not ashamed of it, but I don't think it is relevant in most situations that I face. I love my gods - still find it difficult to decide who is the best between Lord Krishna and Lord Shiva. I love my epics and I do delve on the philosophies and ideas presented in them. The stories present in them have been a part &amp;amp; parcel of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not just thoughts. There are also some actions I do in this regard. I pray everyday in the morning. I apply ash to my forehead everyday (even though I am supposedly an Iyengar). I observe some of the rituals like 'Tarpanam' regularly. I celebrate all the regular Hindu festivals with puja and eagerly consume all the goodies prepared at those times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does all this make me a staunch Hindu? Some might say yes and others might say no. I personally feel that while these aspects have a place but there is more to following hinduism. There is one thought that stands out. I have never felt the need to assert my religion anywhere in my life. I hope it stays that way always and that is another part of what I like about being a Hindu. There is no need to prove to anyone that I am a Hindu (I am not speaking of other religions because I don't know much about them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="recent-events"&gt;Recent events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is all good. But for the past few days, things happening around me are disturbing. For me they are &lt;em&gt;just disturbing&lt;/em&gt;, but for the people involved it, they are painful. There are a few of them I want to mention here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first issue that comes to my mind is the Hijab row. This has been discussed a lot in the media and elsewhere, so I am not going to be able to add any more information to the discussion. The only thing I would like to express here is a thought which came to me on this whole issue. Everyday when I used to go to my office, I would apply ash to my forehead. I attend meetings and discussions with all my team members wearing it. Nobody has asked anything about it. I wear it also when I visit malls or other areas. Again no issues. I have worn it when I visited my school or college in the earlier part of my life. This applying of ash is surely related to my faith. In my mind, I believe that it will protect me. Now the question in my mind is: If I am allowed to do that all the time, I am not sure why a girl can't wear a hijab to her school if &lt;em&gt;she wants to&lt;/em&gt;, based on her faith. How is it different? Again, much more learned people and esteemed institutions might differ with me and I am no one to question to them - I am just expressing what I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next incident was about a student's namaz prayer video shared by another student and that causing an uproar. After this, the student's institution ruled that the student should no longer do the prayers in the premises. I have seen my friends performing their prayers in workplaces of different companies that I have worked in. No one has ever raised an issue about this. If workplaces can be accomodative, I am not sure why it is a problem in a college. Also in the context of this student, she has been performing the prayers for a long time before. And now this has changed. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the incident related to linking hindu festivals to vegetarianism and that leading to violence (while I am a vegetarian, Hindus in general are not - to me it is a choice). Recently I heard about attacks on religious processions and subsequent complaints about targetted demolitions. In both these cases, it is very difficult to know the full truth for a ordinary person like me. There are news reports claiming all sorts of things and it is difficult to know what the truth is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But whatever the case is, these incidents don't give me any good feeling about the country I belong to and live in. It seems that suddenly hindu people need to assert themselves (or even force upon others) as being hindus. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-way-of-being-a-hindu"&gt;My way of being a Hindu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am repeating myself but I have to say that all of these incidents don't give me a good feeling. I am not a very learned person (especially in the context of religion). But the persona I have seen to exist in &lt;em&gt;"my world" - my country&lt;/em&gt;, is a loving one. That persona can accept people for what they are and respect their choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I care as much for all my friends whether they are named Amar, Akbar or Antony (not real names) and that is essential in my mind. I have learnt a lot from all my friends and I am grateful for it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't speak for everyone in the world but I speak from my own roots and my own experience. Based on that I say this - I am part of a religion with 33 crore gods and a concept of &lt;em&gt;ishta daivam&lt;/em&gt; (favorite diety). That religion does not need me to think that there has to be only one way. It seems counter-intuitive to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="last-word"&gt;Last word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This life is precious. Every life is precious. Instead of propogating &lt;em&gt;"the one idea"&lt;/em&gt; as the only idea, it is much better to have a confluence of many ideas and allow people to chose theirs and live their own lives with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="India"></category><category term="people"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="moderation"></category></entry></feed>