<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Starting Point - India</title><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/feeds/india.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.nacnez.com/</id><updated>2023-01-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>The flogging bulldozer which broke the bridge</title><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/flogging-bulldozer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-01-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Srinivas Narayanan</name></author><id>tag:www.nacnez.com,2023-01-14:/flogging-bulldozer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is the bureaucracy changing - Polarization seeping in?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="admonition tip"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;TL;DR&lt;p&gt;We have seen divisive politics around us for some time now. It seems this has seeped into the bureaucracy, which is more interested in posturing than doing their job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure" style="width: 800px; height: auto; max-width: 100%;"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Representing Bureaucracy" src="https://www.nacnez.com/images/bureaucracy.jpg" style="width: 800px; height: auto; max-width: 100%;"/&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Representing Bureaucracy: Photo by © Jorge Royan / &lt;a href="http://www.royan.com.ar"&gt;http://www.royan.com.ar&lt;/a&gt; / CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime back, I heard the news of municipalities using bulldozers to raze done illegal constructions. "Illegal" is supposed to be clear term, but recently there seems to be nuances to it that I was not aware. But I let it go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I heard about policemen flogging people in public. This was really disturbing; the comparisons with Taliban did not feel misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the bridge broke down killing a lot of people. That hurt. I could no longer remain quiet and decided to dig deeper. But, I couldn't get to it immediately. But better late than never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dismantling-bulldozer"&gt;&lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;Dismantling Bulldozer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These events happened long time back, but the internet always has the answer. You still have to know where to look. &lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;ThePrint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has been one of the publications that I have been following for a long time and I trust them. So I decided to try there first (references at the end). I had heard about these bulldozer events in their podcast, but the context had slipped away. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bulldozer culture seems to have started in UP where the CM Yogi used it as a tool to bring law and order changes. He eliminated powerful criminals doing this and was rewarded by the people by getting re-elected. That seems to have started the trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other BJP state CMs took notice. Now, we come to the part where the problem starts. Multiple incidents seem to be reported in Madhya Pradesh, where the CM used the Bulldozer to penalize criminal activity or rioting. There is no law to do this, and the excuse given seems to be demolition of encroachments. As per the law (which varies from state to state), the minimum requirement is that the evicted person must be given notice. ThePrint says that this was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other BJP managed states followed suit and the trend seemed to be clear. The Bulldozer acting on "illegal construction" is going to be the tool of choice to "discipline" certain sects of people. At least that is the feeling I got after reading these articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let me step back. May be, I am biased in saying the above statement. One thing is clear. The municipality (bureaucracy) demolition of illegal construction for any reason, without giving notice, is a breach of their contract with the people. Something is out of whack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="public-flogging"&gt;&lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;Public Flogging&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flogging incident had a left a bad taste in me from the time it happened. The place it happened was &lt;span class="bold-angry"&gt;Gujarat - Ground 0&lt;/span&gt;. I again dug through articles on ThePrint and this is what I gathered. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sarpanch of the village had promised to conduct a &lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for the people, and he decided to fulfill the promise. The location was close to a mosque and the folks from the mosque asked to ensure that the Garba shouldn't disturb their &lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Id&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; preparations. The Garba happened. It is not clear how much of a disturbance it was, but there was some stone pelting. The police caught some people who were alleged to have done this. At this point, it seems that this was a regrettable incident. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then it turned into a catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policemen (couple of people) took 3 of the alleged muslim youth and flogged then in public to the cheers of surrounding public. The Sarpanch was also egging them on. The "people egging on" makes me feel sick, but the police flogging citizens of India is down right heinous. In movies, I have seen police brutality, but those are shown to be done in the confines of the cell or lockup. Here we are talking about creating a public spectacle. This is gross misuse of power and completely unconstitutional. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching signal I got was that government officials wanted to make a name for themselves in the context of religious extremism. Instead of doing their job of controlling crime, they were committing crime in the open, to earn brownie points from the majority population or their powerful leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/author/shekhargupta/"&gt;Shekhar Gupta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in his article laments about the lack of political voice to call out this atrocity, my worry is that the bureaucracy is not just corrupt now (which I think it was to a good extent). They have become bigoted and vain in the context of religion &amp;amp; minorities. There is a commission ordered for probe, but I don't think there has been any real action taken. This makes me feel that the norm is changing. I am worried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="broken-bridge"&gt;&lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;Broken Bridge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports on the bridge collapse were heart-wrenching. I have included some reports below which are really disturbing. The failures were at multiple levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The maintenance contract of the bridge was given to a watch company. I really can't understand the sensibility in it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the bridge was opened after maintenance, there was no checking or certification done by the Municipality. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The crowd control on the bridge was not done properly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the victims complain about delay in providing rescue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows corruption and lack of any responsibility by the authorities at multiple levels. It looks like the municipal authorities were "busy" doing other things. I am not aware of what these are, but I have to wonder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-do-i-make-of-this"&gt;&lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;What do I make of this?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have related 3 different incidents happening in a chronological timeline. While these are disconnected incidents, there are a few thin strands. All have the bureaucracy involved it in some way. These incidents show corruption in the system (which has been there for long), but they don't stop there. I feel there is some kind of posture change involved here. There seems to be misuse of power to target certain sections of society based on "specific criteria" instead of the earlier universal application of corruption. I am extremely worried about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bureaucracy seems to think it is important to send the right signals to specific communities instead of ensuring that real work gets done, and the safety of people is ensured. I hope I am wrong, but the smoke does exist. If you think I am wrong, I would love to hear about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;&lt;span class="bold-calm"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;Dismantling Bulldozer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/theprint-essential/bulldozers-go-after-illegal-encroachments-from-mp-to-delhi-but-the-law-requires-a-notice/924105/"&gt;ThePrint: Bulldozers go after ‘illegal encroachments’ from MP to Delhi, but the law requires a notice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/politics/big-hit-with-bjp-bulldozers-now-rolling-in-gujarat-uttarakhand-coming-soon-to-karnataka/926715/"&gt;ThePrint: Big hit with BJP, bulldozers now rolling in Gujarat &amp;amp; Uttarakhand, coming soon to Karnataka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/bulldozers-in-shaheen-bagh-but-no-demolition-how-residents-averted-law-and-order-situation/948861/"&gt;ThePrint: Bulldozers in Shaheen Bagh, but no demolition: How residents averted ‘law-and-order situation’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulldozer_politics"&gt;Wikipedia: Bulldozer politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://thewire.in/rights/the-bulldozer-is-reshaping-our-cities-and-our-imaginations"&gt;TheWire: The Bulldozer Is Reshaping Our Cities and Our Imaginations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;Public Flogging&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/gujarat-police-chief-orders-probe-into-kheda-flogging-incident-outfit-sends-legal-notices-to-dgp-govt/1158306/"&gt;ThePrint: Gujarat police chief orders probe into Kheda flogging incident; outfit sends legal notices to DGP, govt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/new-sarpanch-vowed-to-start-garba-in-village-sparked-clashes-undhelas-muslim-residents-say/1159890/"&gt;ThePrint: New sarpanch vowed to start garba in village, sparked clashes, Undhela’s Muslim residents say&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/gujarat-flogging-muslim-villagers-affidavit-blames-kheda-dsp-bjp-mla-undhela-sarpanch/1165029/"&gt;ThePrint: Gujarat flogging: Muslim villager’s affidavit blames Kheda DSP, BJP MLA, Undhela sarpanch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/national-interest/press-mute-for-indian-muslims-how-gujarat-flogging-shows-up-secular-silence-of-indian-politics/1168603/"&gt;Press mute for Indian Muslims — how Gujarat flogging shows up ‘secular’ silence of Indian politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="bold-green"&gt;Broken Bridge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/the-ruckus-that-led-to-gujarats-morbi-bridge-collapse-the-challenges-facing-rescue-teams/1188964/"&gt;ThePrint: The ‘ruckus’ that led to Gujarat’s Morbi bridge collapse &amp;amp; the challenges facing rescue teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/kept-calling-but-nobody-came-morbi-bridge-survivors-stories-of-terror-abandonment/1192019/"&gt;ThePrint: ‘Kept calling but nobody came’: Morbi bridge survivors’ stories of terror &amp;amp; abandonment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/opinion/newsmaker-of-the-week/morbi-bridge-dents-not-just-the-gujarat-model-its-an-infrastructure-hole-india-cant-unsee/1198160/"&gt;ThePrint: Morbi bridge dents not just the Gujarat model. It’s an infrastructure hole India can’t unsee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/morbi-bridge-collapse-incident-highlights-cronyism-perpetuated-in-gujarat-says-cong/1217909/"&gt;Morbi bridge collapse incident highlights cronyism perpetuated in Gujarat, says Cong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/sc-terms-morbi-bridge-collapse-as-an-enormous-tragedy-asks-gujarat-hc-to-periodically-monitor-probe/1228367/"&gt;SC terms Morbi bridge collapse as an ‘enormous tragedy, asks Gujarat HC to periodically monitor probe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://theprint.in/india/gujarat-bridge-collapse-it-was-heart-wrenching-eyewitness-recount-morbi-horror/1188665/"&gt;Gujarat Bridge Collapse: “It was heart wrenching…” eyewitness recount Morbi horror&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="small-italicized-green"&gt;Aum sarvam SriKrishnarpanam astu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="opinion"></category><category term="India"></category><category term="people"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="bureaucracy"></category><category term="polarization"></category></entry><entry><title>My India changing</title><link href="https://www.nacnez.com/india-extreme.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Srinivas Narayanan</name></author><id>tag:www.nacnez.com,2022-04-25:/india-extreme.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Changing face of India - getting extreme&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a write up on how I feel about my India changing in the context of religion. This is just a representation of how I feel. If it makes sense to you then you can consider listening to it, else you can surely ignore it (not that I need to say this &lt;span class="emoji"&gt;😅&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-life-religion"&gt;My life &amp;amp; religion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally don't parade the fact that I am a Hindu. I am not ashamed of it, but I don't think it is relevant in most situations that I face. I love my gods - still find it difficult to decide who is the best between Lord Krishna and Lord Shiva. I love my epics and I do delve on the philosophies and ideas presented in them. The stories present in them have been a part &amp;amp; parcel of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not just thoughts. There are also some actions I do in this regard. I pray everyday in the morning. I apply ash to my forehead everyday (even though I am supposedly an Iyengar). I observe some of the rituals like 'Tarpanam' regularly. I celebrate all the regular Hindu festivals with puja and eagerly consume all the goodies prepared at those times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does all this make me a staunch Hindu? Some might say yes and others might say no. I personally feel that while these aspects have a place but there is more to following hinduism. There is one thought that stands out. I have never felt the need to assert my religion anywhere in my life. I hope it stays that way always and that is another part of what I like about being a Hindu. There is no need to prove to anyone that I am a Hindu (I am not speaking of other religions because I don't know much about them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="recent-events"&gt;Recent events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is all good. But for the past few days, things happening around me are disturbing. For me they are &lt;em&gt;just disturbing&lt;/em&gt;, but for the people involved it, they are painful. There are a few of them I want to mention here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first issue that comes to my mind is the Hijab row. This has been discussed a lot in the media and elsewhere, so I am not going to be able to add any more information to the discussion. The only thing I would like to express here is a thought which came to me on this whole issue. Everyday when I used to go to my office, I would apply ash to my forehead. I attend meetings and discussions with all my team members wearing it. Nobody has asked anything about it. I wear it also when I visit malls or other areas. Again no issues. I have worn it when I visited my school or college in the earlier part of my life. This applying of ash is surely related to my faith. In my mind, I believe that it will protect me. Now the question in my mind is: If I am allowed to do that all the time, I am not sure why a girl can't wear a hijab to her school if &lt;em&gt;she wants to&lt;/em&gt;, based on her faith. How is it different? Again, much more learned people and esteemed institutions might differ with me and I am no one to question to them - I am just expressing what I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next incident was about a student's namaz prayer video shared by another student and that causing an uproar. After this, the student's institution ruled that the student should no longer do the prayers in the premises. I have seen my friends performing their prayers in workplaces of different companies that I have worked in. No one has ever raised an issue about this. If workplaces can be accomodative, I am not sure why it is a problem in a college. Also in the context of this student, she has been performing the prayers for a long time before. And now this has changed. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the incident related to linking hindu festivals to vegetarianism and that leading to violence (while I am a vegetarian, Hindus in general are not - to me it is a choice). Recently I heard about attacks on religious processions and subsequent complaints about targetted demolitions. In both these cases, it is very difficult to know the full truth for a ordinary person like me. There are news reports claiming all sorts of things and it is difficult to know what the truth is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But whatever the case is, these incidents don't give me any good feeling about the country I belong to and live in. It seems that suddenly hindu people need to assert themselves (or even force upon others) as being hindus. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-way-of-being-a-hindu"&gt;My way of being a Hindu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am repeating myself but I have to say that all of these incidents don't give me a good feeling. I am not a very learned person (especially in the context of religion). But the persona I have seen to exist in &lt;em&gt;"my world" - my country&lt;/em&gt;, is a loving one. That persona can accept people for what they are and respect their choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I care as much for all my friends whether they are named Amar, Akbar or Antony (not real names) and that is essential in my mind. I have learnt a lot from all my friends and I am grateful for it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't speak for everyone in the world but I speak from my own roots and my own experience. Based on that I say this - I am part of a religion with 33 crore gods and a concept of &lt;em&gt;ishta daivam&lt;/em&gt; (favorite diety). That religion does not need me to think that there has to be only one way. It seems counter-intuitive to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="last-word"&gt;Last word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This life is precious. Every life is precious. Instead of propogating &lt;em&gt;"the one idea"&lt;/em&gt; as the only idea, it is much better to have a confluence of many ideas and allow people to chose theirs and live their own lives with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="India"></category><category term="people"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="moderation"></category><category term="polarization"></category></entry></feed>