<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Starting Point - Podcasting</title><link href="http://www.nacnez.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.nacnez.com/feeds/podcasting.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.nacnez.com/</id><updated>2015-05-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Thou shall listen to Podcasts - Part II</title><link href="http://www.nacnez.com/thou-shall-listen-to-podcasts-part-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-05-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Srinivas Narayanan</name></author><id>tag:www.nacnez.com,2015-05-04:/thou-shall-listen-to-podcasts-part-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to share the podcasts I listen to - part 2.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ok. I did say that I will bring the next installment quickly (you can find the &lt;a href="http://www.nacnez.com/thou-shall-listen-to-podcasts-part-1.html"&gt;previous one here&lt;/a&gt;) But my life and me got in the way. But, better late than never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasts Set 2 - The Software Developer's Topper List&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set of podcasts are focused on software development, open source software and technology related. I listen to a good number of such shows and in this installment I am going to share my top three picks. Hopefully I will follow up with more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Software Engineering Radio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Software Engineering Radio Logo" src="http://www.se-radio.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/se-radio-logo.png" style="float:right; width:40%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.se-radio.net/"&gt;Software Engineering Radio&lt;/a&gt;, as the name suggests, is focused on Software engineering. I would say it is a must listen for professional developers. The topics covered vary from software engineering related topics - agile, continuous delivery, architecture related and open source frameworks. The discussion is very technical in nature (some of the most technical discussions I have heard on a podcast) but it still tries to give the listener a good overview of the subject. The discussions are reasonably long (around 45 - 60 minutes), so there is time to explore the topic to some extent. The guests are mostly leaders in the field and/or head honchos of the open source projects that is being discussed. The hosts are a team of developers themselves (some of them very renowned in their own right) and help the steer the discussion so that it is developer focused.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the recent topics I have listened to are Apache Storm, Continuous Delivery, Logging infrastructure, CQRS, Kafka etc. Recently these shows have become more frequent as well (hope it stays that way). If you are a developer and want to try podcast listening, this one is something you would want to start with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/se-radio"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of SE Radio" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Cloudcast&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Cloudcast Logo" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-xtXs8yJ2Ll0/VNopnCEwhDI/AAAAAAAABWM/w_ZHJlzFZlQ/s1600/Cloudcast-Logo-2015-Banner-Blue.png" style="float:right; width:40%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thecloudcast.net/"&gt;The Cloudcast&lt;/a&gt; started as a cloud technologies podcast. At that time, lots of coverage used to be on Cloud platform vendors and products out there. But close to an year back, they have started focusing a lot on open source projects on cloud and distributed computing  and devops related topics. These podcasts are generally short and to the point. The hosts try not get into a lot of depth but try to get the guests to provide high level but useful information and more importantly trends. Recently they have added byte sized versions of the podcast which provide very short introductions of dev and devops topics. You might find those specific ones either useful or trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I primarily find the podcast discussions providing me a lot of breadth of knowledge in the space. The hosts are really good too. Brian is very sharp and to the point. Aaron on the other hand brings more fun and cheer. Overall a very good podcast to listen to for the topics they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.buzzsprout.com/3195.rss"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of The Cloudcast" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Floss Weekly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Floss Weekly Logo" src="http://twit.tv/files/imagecache/coverart-feed/coverart/floss1400.jpg" style="float:right; width:30%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twit.tv/show/floss-weekly"&gt;Floss Weekly&lt;/a&gt; is a podcast focused on free and open source software. This is one of the oldest shows in the podcasting planet. The nature of projects could vary a lot in this podcast. I have discovered a &lt;a href="http://synergy-project.org/"&gt;desktop software for controlling multiple computers using a single keyboard and mouse&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ushahidi/Ushahidi_Web"&gt;platform which made Kenyan elections better&lt;/a&gt; through this podcast. It is this variety which draws me to it. The primary criteria of projects participating in it is about them being open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hosts don't get as technical as the other two shows (except for Randal at times), but the show provides a well rounded overview of the project. There is considerable discussion on open source licensing and governance which I don't find in other shows. And that is something I like to get exposed to. So if you are into open source in general and like variety, this is a good podcast to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://feeds.twit.tv/floss.xml"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of Floss Weekly" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done! This is a short one. The top three are out, but there is more to come. I will get them out sooner than later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="podcasting"></category><category term="favorite podcasts"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="creative"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Thou shall listen to Podcasts - Part I</title><link href="http://www.nacnez.com/thou-shall-listen-to-podcasts-part-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-31T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-01-31T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Srinivas Narayanan</name></author><id>tag:www.nacnez.com,2015-01-31:/thou-shall-listen-to-podcasts-part-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to share the podcasts I listen to.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I listen to a lot of podcasts. I really can't remember how it started but getting my smart phone (about 4 years back) is what triggered it. I have listened to a lot of them and found them useful, entertaining, informative and fun. Some of these podcasters even feel like long time friends. Ok, that might be pushing it, but at times I do feel a sort of allegiance and loyalty to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Podcasts" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/podcast.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why Podcasts?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectively, I feel podcasts can act as a good source of information/knowledge which can consumed in a passive manner. I listen to podcasts mostly when I am commuting or exercising (walking!). There are podcasts for almost every topic you can think of. I am primarily focused on technology, software development and startup related podcasts but I know there are a lot more available. While there are podcasts directories which you can use to locate podcasts, I find my podcasts from podcatchers, itunes and from other podcasts (and of course do googling for getting the rss feed link). Most of the podcasts I listen to are produced in the US (wish I could find more from India!!!). That said, they provide a lot of value from my perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Share the goodness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I find it so useful, I thought it would be good to share them with others. I initially thought of just creating a list of all of them and throw it out there. But somehow I felt that was too vanilla. Then I thought of creating a top 10 list but that felt cheesy initially. When I thought more about it and I felt it might be useful for figuring out my own preferences and likings and my ability to judge things. So I attempted to make an objective score for some of the really good podcasts (as per my taste) which I listen to. Only to realize that it is damn difficult to make it objective. So I gave up on that. Finally decided to create a set of subjective groups of podcasts I listen to and share them with you all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasts Set 1 - Distinctive and Fresh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am starting this series with a set of podcasts which I feel have a very distinctive nature. The content they provide (most times) is perceptive and opens your mind to a lot of different thoughts and ideas. Listening to them makes you think, smile and sometimes be amazed. Let us get on with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Spark&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nora Young who anchors Spark" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/57/Nora_Young.jpg/240px-Nora_Young.jpg" style="float:right"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/radio/spark"&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt;, in Nora's words, is a podcast about tech trends and fresh ideas. And I couldn't describe it any better. Nora is the anchor of the show. The podcast is set as a conversation with the listener. Nora makes the listener a part of the journey in which she meets remarkable people and has very deliberate and pleasant conversation with them. These people look at tech in different ways - either to solve problems or just to understand different things. The podcast brings innovative stories on tech trends and how technology affects people and culture. It brings up simple life hacks and cool new ideas. And it is really produced well (it is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spark_(radio_show)"&gt;a radio show by CBC&lt;/a&gt;). The show is done regularly. The music is done well and it connects the various parts of the show nicely. There is a scent of art and creation in the podcast which appeals to creative spirit in us developers (at least I would like to think that :)). It leaves you with an enriched and fresh feeling most of the times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/podcasting/includes/spark.xml"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of Spark" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hanselminutes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scott Hanselman who produces hanselminutes" src="http://www.developerfusion.com/resource/get/content/8330/image/" style="float:right"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://hanselminutes.com/"&gt;Hanselminutes&lt;/a&gt; is a podcast produced by Scott Hanselman. This podcast historically was a .NET developer podcast. But for quite a long time (at least from the time I have been listening), it has not had that focus at all. There are some shows related to .NET for sure. At the same time there are shows on Python, Javascript, Dart, Java etc. as well. Actually forget the programming languages. This guy produces shows on UX, game development, startups, relationships, developer culture, diabetes technologies, iphones etc. Almost anything under the sun - the difference is that he looks at it from an eye of a developer and problem solver. Also, he always will try to NOT make any assumptions on what the listener might know about the topic. He will get the guest to explain the topic without the listener getting lost on jargon speak. The discussion is never long, but whatever is talked would make sense to you and that nugget is something you can carry with you. The way he goes about the discussion is engaging and simple. He does not try to be funny or anything. Just genuine good conversation. The wide variety of topics which he covers makes it very appealing to me. And he is very very regular. So you can expect some interesting conversation every week. Though I have never met him personally, the show sort of makes me feel that I know him somewhat. And he is an open source supporter too!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://feeds.podtrac.com/9dPm65vdpLL1"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of Hanselminutes" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Cognicast&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cognicast latest episode cover art" src="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/5372821be4b0aefc6719057e/537b9f06e4b040994befd67c/54aad9cfe4b0c9d38e1b2771/1422026079312/?format=300w" style="float:right"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://blog.cognitect.com/cognicast/"&gt;Cognicast&lt;/a&gt; is a podcast produced by Cognitect and is hosted by Craig Andera. This is relatively new podcast and leans towards Clojure related topics (since Cognitect is Clojure focused - Rich Hickey is the CTO for crying out loud!). Now I am not a Clojure guy at all but I like the functional leanings of the topics. That said, this podcast is also modeled in the lines of hanselminutes. Apart from technical topics, it covers other kinds of topics as well. Craig keeps the conversation nice and cordial. One of the great things he does is that he allows the guest to flow with what they want to talk and get the maximum out of them. He might nudge them a little here and there but allows them to take the limelight almost completely. Very nice and humble all the time. Some of the discussions I have heard have truly blown my mind. That is why even when there are many clojure heavy discussions on the show, I still listen to them since I get at least something out of it. Another novel part of the show is that allows you to sample lots of different music. The show is young but I find it enjoyable, thought provoking and fresh. I hope Craig keeps going that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update on 3-May-2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The music sampling part of the show got stopped from this year (2015) onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/cognicast"&gt;&lt;img alt="rss feed link of Cognicast" src="http://www.nacnez.com/images/rss-icon.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the first batch out. I will push the next installment very soon!!! Catch you all later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="podcasting"></category><category term="favorite podcasts"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="creative"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry></feed>